In the previous lesson, we talked about where
في الدرس السابق تحدثنا عن
to look for clients and how to apply to work for them.
مكان البحث عن العملاء وكيفية التقدم للعمل.
Now, in this lesson,
وفي هذا الدرس
we will talk about what happens when a client has indeed got an interested in us,
سنتحدث عما سيحدث عندما يكون العميل مهتمًا بالعمل معنا بالفعل
and it's trying to walk on the finite details before starting work.
ونحاول أن نقف عند تفاصيل محددة قبل البدء في العمل.
Now, let's look at our freelancing journey with the client,
الآن هيا ننظر إلى رحلة عملنا الحر مع العميل،
and what this specific lesson is about in that journey.
ونرى ما نتعلمه من هذه الرحلة.
So far, we discussed about finding clients and sending what
حتى الآن ناقشنا طريقة إيجاد العملاء وإرسال
we call expression of interests to them to increase our chances of getting work.
رسائل التعبير عن الاهتمام بالعمل حتى نزيد من فرص الحصول على وظيفة.
Now, once the client has shown interest in working with us and has
الآن، فور إبداء العميل اهتمامه في العمل معنا،
also finalized the contract to start working with us,
وقيامه بعمل العقد ليبدأ العمل معنا،
we can go ahead and start managing the project until completion.
يمكننا المُضي قُدمًا والبدء في إدارة المشروع حتى إنهاءه.
But even before we do that,
ولكن قبل ذلك،
there is an important phase in between,
هناك مرحلة مهمة في المنتصف،
where we discuss the scope and the appropriate pricing framework with the client.
حيث نناقش النطاق وإطار التسعير المناسب مع العميل.
As you go through this lesson,
في هذا الدرس،
you will learn how important this phase can be in a freelancing project.
ستتعلم مدى أهمية هذا الجانب في مشاريع العمل الحر.
The more specific the details are on scope and pricing framework,
فكلما كانت تفاصيل إطار العمل والتسعير محددة،
the smoother will your project be later.
كان العمل على المشروع أسهل لاحقًا.
Let's take a look at what we will cover in this lesson.
هيا ننظر إلى ما سنتناوله في هذا الدرس.
First, we start out by discussing what do we mean by scoping
أولًا سنبدأ بمناقشة المقصود بنطاق
the project and best practices to scope a project before we started.
المشروع وأفضل الممارسات لتحديد نطاق المشروع قبل بدء العمل.
We will also discuss the common types of
وسنناقش أيضًا الأنواع الشائعة
pricing frameworks and how to figure out the best fit,
من أنظمة التسعير وكيفية اختيار النظام الأفضل،
keeping the client in mind and the correlation between the scope and the pricing.
مع مراعاة مصلحة العميل ومراعاة العلاقة بين نطاق المشروع ونظام التسعير.
Then we'll talk about how to set a rate and
ثم سنتحدث عن كيفية تحديد معدل
fixed costs when you start out your freelancing carrier.
الميزانية الثابتة عندما تبدأ في مهنة العمل الحر.
Then we'll touch upon non-disclosure agreements and service agreements,
ثم سنتطرَّق إلى اتفاقات عدم الإفصاح واتفاقات الخدمات
and how to avoid usual pitfalls before starting a project.
وكيفية تجنب المشاكل المعتادة قبل أن نبدأ المشروع.
Lastly, we'll discuss an edge case,
وأخيرًا سنتناول حالة متطرفة،
a situation that is less common in
وهو موقف أقل شيوعًا في
a regular freelancing project and best practice to deal with it.
مشاريع العمل الحر وسنعرف كيفية التعامل معه.
By the end of this lesson,
ومع نهاية الدرس،
you'll be able to work with the client,
ستكون قادرًا على التعاون مع العميل
to create the project scope by applying freelancing best practices.
لإنشاء نطاق المشروع باستخدام أفضل ممارسات العمل الحر.
Determine the pricing framework by deciding between
وستكون قادرًا على تحديد إطار التسعير المناسب بالاختيار بين
fixed cost or time and materials contract based on client needs.
العقد القائم على نظام التكلفة المحددة أو تكلفة الوقت والمواد طبقًا لاحتياج العميل.
Lastly, you'll be able to formalize the initiation of the project,
وأخيرًا ستكون قادرًا على إضفاء الطابع الرسمي على بدء المشروع،
including any non-disclosure agreements or service agreements involved in the project.
ليشمل اتفاقية عدم الإفصاح أو اتفاقات خدمات المشروع.